Guide to the Civil War Collection, 1857-1869 M0023
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Civil War Collection,
1857-1869
M0023
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
0.5 Linear feet
Barnes, Willam
Campbell, J. C.
Gerst, Joseph S.
Long, Rich
Martindale, Edward
Melhorn, John Wesley
Moore, Edward
Moore, Laura
Moore, Orlando Hurley
Spencer, Israel
Scope and Contents Note:
This collection includes letters, a diary, photographs, and military documents of several different individuals and families pertaining to military matters as well as life back home.
Access Restrictions:
None.
- Series M0023a Diaries of John Wesley Melhorn, 1862-1863
  Scope and Contents Note:
  Typescript copy of the diaries of John Wesley Melhorn,1862 April 17 -1862 September 10 and 1862 December 16 -1863 May 10, reporting on action in the Shenandoah Valley, Seven Pines, Second Manassas, Chancellorville, and Frederickburg. Melhorn was a Capt. of Company C, 10th Virginia Infantry.
- Series M0023b Letter of Rich Long, 1863
  Letter of Rich Long, Lt. Colonel in the 73rd Ohio Volunteers, Infantry, to Gen. W. D. Whipple, 1863 December 25, endorsed by Gen. O. O. Howard.
- Series M0023c Letter of J. C. Campbell, 1863
  Letter of J. C. Campbell to Adda Leighton, 1863 November 13, describing the death of Miss Leighton's brother.
- Series M0023d Letter of J. B. N., n.d.
  Letter from J. B. N. to "Friend Quiney" stationed at Port Hudson, Louisiana, discussing Negro troops.
- Series M0023e Letters of Israel Spencer, 1862-1865
  Letters from Israel Spencer to relatives describing campaigns in Virginia, Chancellorsville, and Gettysburg with the 136th New York Volunteer Infantry, Company A, 1862 August 28 -1865 June 13.
- Series M0023f Moore Family Letters, 1861-1865
  These letters are written to Theodore H. and Edward M. Moore by Edward and Laura Moore and other friends in the army and at home. They primarily discuss social life and school teaching, with some mention of draft dodgers and camp life. Also included is an obituary for Theodore F. Moore and poems and essays by family members.
- Series M0023g William Barnes Civil War Pass, 1864
  William Barnes' Civil War pass to the White House, 1864 June 1.
  Provenance:
  Gift of the estate of Thomas M. Marshall
- Series M0023h Col. Orlando Hurley Moore Civil War Papers, 1863, 1943
  Typescript copy of remarks by Col. Moore prior to the battle of Tebbs Bend, Kentucky, 1863 July 4; clippings about Col. Moore and his part in breaking up the "Pacific Republic, ca. 1943; and a letter from his daughter Jesse Moore Loveridge, 1943.
  Gift of Jesse Moore Loveridge, July 1943
- Series M0023i Col. Edward Martindale Civil War Letters and Photographs, 1863-1865
  Biograhpical Note:
  Edward Martindale served with the 26th New Jersey Vol. Regiment under General Hooker, the 83rd Regiment, U. S. Infantry (Colored), and the 118th Regiment (Colored). He commanded the Provisional Brigade, U. S. Colored Troops, 18th Army Corps and other African American units. Martindale was credited with the capture of Libby Prison.
  Included in this series are approximately fifty letters from Martindale to his wife, 1863 April 3 to 1865 March 9; three photographs; and one commemorative document (in oversize storage).
- Series M0023j Lee's General Order Number Nine, 1865
  Facsimile of Lee's farewell to the Army of Northern Virginia, 1865 April 10.
- Series M0023k Army Muster Rolls, 1857, 1869
  Army muster rolls from Fort Duncan, Texas, 1857, and from Fort Wayne, Michigan, 1869.
  Gift of Stephen Keachie
- Series M0023l Civil War Oath of Joseph S. Gerst, 1865
  Document of oath to support and defend the constitution of the United States and support the laws of slave emancipation, signed by Joseph S. Gerst, 1865 September 13.
  Gift of S. J. Lisberger